Guide to the Individual manuscripts, publications, and artifacts, 150 AD. - 2014 MS2135
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Individual manuscripts, publications, and artifacts
150 AD. - Circa 2014
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Huffman, J. Ford
MS2135
30 Linear Feet
This artificial collection was created to manage documents that are too small to be separate collections of their own. Includes individual manuscripts, undated; Elbridge Colby's "The National Guard of the United States", 1903-1945; Book Arts Specimens, 1600 ca- 1850 ca.; Performing Arts Material, 1890-1980; Gay and lesbian publications, 1994-1998; Washingtoniana magazines, journals, and newsletters, 1879-1974; Washington associations, clubs, lodges, and societies, 1845-1948.
Restrictions on Access
This collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The items in the collection came to the library over time through both purchases and donations.
Historical or Biographical Note
This artificial collection was created to manage documents that are too small to be separate collections of their own.
Collection Organization
Organized into 11 series: Individual manuscripts, typescripts, and images, Elbridge Colby's "The National Guard of the United States," Book arts specimens, Performing arts materials, Gay and lesbian publications and ephemera, Washingtoniana magazines, journals, and newsletters, Washington associations, clubs, lodges, and societies, Middle East maps, photographs, newspapers, Collection of European periodicals dealing with the Armenia, American political publications, and Lewis Hotel Training School Course materials
Social life and customs; Politics and government; Medicine; Alleys; Housing; Slavery; Adams Morgan (Washington, D.C.); England; Great Britain; Rye House Plot, 1683; United States National Guard; United States -- History; Urban renewal; Shaw (Washington, D.C.); Foggy Bottom (Washington, D.C.); Olney (Md.); Gaithersburg (Md.); Washington (D.C.); Antisemitism; Politics and government; Washington, George; Perske, Martha; Sumner, Charles; Twain, Mark; Corcoran, W. W. (William Wilson); Spingarn, Joel Elias; Lee, Robert Edwin; Russell, William, Lord; Davis, Jefferson; Colby, Elbridge; Adams, John; Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885; Blodget, Samuel; Henry, Joseph; Custis, George Washington Parke; Huffman, J. Ford
- Individual manuscripts, typescripts, artifacts, and images, MS2135 Series 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains manuscripts, correspondence, a bond, reports, papers. Most of these items relate to some aspect of the history of Washington, D.C.
  Separated Materials
  The item Document in Greek on papyrus was removed from this artificial collection and added to the Special Collections catalog. It is discoverable using the GW online catalog and housed in the Special Collections book collection (vault CG45). The call no. is PA3300.A6 S53 catalog records is for the title Document on Greek papyrus.
  In 2020 Todd M. Hickey and James G. Keenan published a treatment of this document titled An Enslaved Woman Resold. Published in Papyrologica Lugduno-Batava Volume XXXVII.
  Arrangement
  This is an artificial series in an artificial collection created by staff and it continues to be added to periodically. This new content is added to the end of the list of content.
  - Shakespeare Club of Washington D.C., records Vol. 1, 04/13/1872-06/16/1873 -- --ca. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    This item contains the club constitution, minute books, and membership rolls. The material dates from April 13, 1872 to May 1, 1875. The club's constitution was adopted on December 28 1869. The club formed for meetings generally weekly for the reading of plays by Shakespeare and modern popular playwrights. Both men and women were members. Formerly Ind Ms. Bd. 73
  - Shakespeare Club of Washington D.C., records Vol. 2, 10/11/1873-05/01/1875 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    See also 0029#00157
  - Kinesiology notebook, 1965-1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Notebook for Physical Education 50, a course with Helen B. Lawrence, Feb.-May, 1965, at George Washington University. The paper is by Jane Boydstun. This is an example of a GW student paper. Formerly Ind Ms. Bd. 6
  - Historical photography as a tool in historic preservation: a community application, 11/30/1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the historical photography tool requirement for the American studies Department, George Washington University. November 20, 1981. The author is Sandra Lee Kurtinitis. Sandra Kurtinitis donated this paper in 1981. This document is a sample of GW student paper. Formerly Ind Ms. Bd. 70
  - Adams-Morgan: democratic action fails to save a neighborhood, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Prepared for George Washington University class, Administration in Metropolitan-Area Governments II. Includes bibliographical references (leaves 78-81). The author is Hope Marindin. This paper is an example if a GW student paper. Formerly Ind Ms. Bd. 108
  - The housing problem in the District of Columbia, 05/14/1941 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Paper prepared for Sociology 28-B (at George Washington University?). The author if the paper is Howard E. Stingle. This paper is an example of a GW student paper. Formerly Ind Ms. Bd. 76
  - The work of the Alley Dwelling Authority in Washington, D.C., 05/14/1941 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Paper prepared for Sociology 28-B (at George Washington University?). Author is Eldon W. Wingerd. This paper is an example of a GW student paper. Formerly Ind Ms. Bd. 75
  - History of the Quartermaster Corps Project: located at the George Washington University, 12/31/1945 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Under contracts W 44-109-qm-329 and W 44-109-qm-675 with the U.S. Army Quartermaster Corps, Research and Development Branch, Military Planning Division, the project's purpose was to make a survey of sources of interest to the Branch and to procure the documents or make abstracts of them. Reports were received from the War and Navy Departments, National Research Council, and several British and Canadian government offices. The author is Susan Elizabeth Boyer. Formerly Ind Ms. Bd. 7
  - The Philosophies of Shakespeare and the three romances, 09/25/1919-06/28/1919 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    This notebook created by Franklin J. Jackson was apparently a project for a class at The George Washington University. Formerly IMB #8
  - Physics lectures, notes [Vol. 1], 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    This volume is an example of lectures and notes and was the property of William L. Cheney. Formerly Ind Ms. Bd. 86
  - Physics lectures, notes [Vol. 2], 1916-1917 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    This volume is an example of lectures and notes and was the property of William L. Cheney. A note on the title page says "Physics 500. Rice Institute 1916-1917." Formerly Ind Ms. Bd. 86
  - The counseling interview, 1955 ca. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Lecture given in a course at GW. Taught by Mitchell Dreese, professor of Psychology and Dean of Summer Sessions. From title page: "Lecture given to the Air Force Manpower Management Course by Dr. Mitchell Dreese of The George Washington University." Formerly Ind Ms. Bd. 78
  - Chemistry II Laboratory book: Russell Barker Munroe, 10/16/1905-06/22/1906 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Russell Barker Munroe was GW student and the son of Charles E. Munroe a Chemistry Professor at George Washington University, 1892-1918. This notebook contains notes on results of experiments. This is an example of student notes taken while a student attending a GW course. Formerly Ind Ms. Bd. 87
  - A trip from Mystic, Connecticut to Northern Vermont, 08/22/1921-08/25/1921 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Title page reads "A TRIP TO MYSTIC, CONNECTICUT, TO NORTHERN VERMONT, August 22-25, 1921. An Automobile ride from St. Albans to Montgomery Centre, along the Missisquoi River, the Birthplace and boyhood home of Dr. Samuel Harrison Greene." This document contains handwritten passages, one letter, postcards, and photographs. This volume came from ACC#571
  - Supremacy: a play in three acts, 1930 ca. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    The address of the author Thomas C. Kemp is listed on the title page as 81 Olton Boulevard East, Acocks Green, Birmingham. There is also a note attached to the original catalog record that this work was published in London by George Allen & Unwin, 1932, c.1931. Formerly Ind Ms. Bd. 90
  - Washington Barracks, medical record book, 02/1900-12/1907 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    This volume contains manuscript monthly reports on the status of water supply, sanitation, food supply, plumbing, ventilation, and clothing and health of soldiers at Washington Barracks. Also reports births and deaths at the Barracks. Established 1797, first known as Washington Arsenal; later Washington Barracks; in the 1930s named Fort Humphreys; in 1939 assumed the name of the Army War College which it served; in 1948 renamed Fort Lesley J. McNair. From the card catalog card, it is possible that this ledger may have been purchased by the department in 1995. Formerly Ind Ms. Bd. 104 f
  - Medical Society of the District of Columbia. Library, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Medical Society of the District of Columbia, founded 1817. This bound volume may be dated in the 1880s. Summary: Entries for 829 titles dating from the seventeenth century through 1884, with most dating from 1850-1884. Formerly Ind Ms. Bd. 91 f
  - Letter, George J. Abbot to Abiel Abbot, 05/15/1837 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    Abbot writes to his Unitarian minister uncle in Petersborough N.H., describing the state of Unitarianism and other churches in Washington, and the state of education in the city. He mentions William Cranch, Chief Justice of the Circuit Court of the District of Columbia, as a Unitarian, and speaks approvingly of the series of lectures given by Charles Follen. The letter is signed. This letter was purchased by Gelman library in 1983. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, John Adams to Enoch Reynolds, 09/07/1832 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    This letter requests payment of interest, due in June, on a loan to Columbian College, later to be George Washington University, from John Quincy Adams, the writer's father. Enoch Reynolds esq. was the Treasurer of the Columbian College. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, John Quincy Adams to George Wood, 10/20/1837 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    Content of letter: to the Treasurer of the Columbian College, asking the payment of interest in the amount of $684.64 on the debt owed to him by Columbian College, which later became George Washington University. With cover, and receipt, 1842 March 5, Washington, signed by J.Q. Adams, for the sum of $8,796.23 received from the treasurer of Columbian College, later George Washington University. The letter is used by Elmer Kayser in his book Bricks without straw, p. 88. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Correspondence, 04/19/1940-05/18/1954 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    Typed letter, signed, 1940 April 19, from Henry Morgenthau, Jr., concerning U.S. savings bonds; two typed letters signed from Gilbert Highet, concerning Highet's authorship of several books. Gift of Donald Armstrong. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Receipt, 04/23/1912 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    Charles Wakefield Cadman was an American composer. This item is a signed typewritten receipt for $50 for the fund of copying Cadman's opera, Daoma, in ink. "Denver, Colorado, April 23, 1912 Received of Francis La Flesche the sum of 450 (fifty dollars) and applied to the fund of copying the opera DAOMA in ink." The source of this item is unknown. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Charles Carroll to Daniel Carroll, 05/21/1804 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    This letter requests from Daniel Carroll of Duddington, President of the Bank of Washington, some certificates, the interest to be paid in London and expresses doubts that the bridge over the Potomac River can be rebuilt for the sum the directors estimate, and that the bridge will soon be financially solvent. Gelman library purchased this letter in 1985. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letters, W.W. Corcoran, 02/13/1841-06/25/1883 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    W.W. Corcoran was an American banker and philanthropist; founder of Riggs Bank and the Corcoran Gallery of Art. The three letters, 1841 and 1883, concern financial transactions. The letter dated 1869 April 15, mentions enclosure of the catalog of his gallery. The letter dated 1877 Dec. 4, Washington, to James Grant Wilson, and letter, 1883 Feb. 20, Washington, to Gabriel Harrison, ask for information on forthcoming publications from these authors. Purchased by Gelman library in 1986. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Richard Crockett to his brother and sister, 09/08/1862 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    Sergeant Richard Crockett, of the 19th Maine Regiment of the Union Army, did not take part in the 2nd Battle of Bull Run, and asks for any news of other Maine regiments in this battle. He mentions marching between forts in the District of Columbia, such as Fort Davis, Fort Dupont, and Fort Baker, and across the Potomac into Virginia, and includes a map of these areas and the Potomac River. He expresses a desire to fight the rebel forces and to hear news from home. Gelman Library purchsed this letter in 1983. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, George Washington Parke Custis to D. Rose, undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
    This letter acknowledges receipt of, and complies with, request for George Washington Parke Custis's autograph. The letter is dated Nov. 6. The year is not provided. The original catalog card indicates the letter falls somewhere between 1820 and 1857. Logan Cowgill donated this letter in 1972. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, George Washington Parke Custis to Directors of the Washington Bridge Company, 11/13/1831 ca. (Box 5, Folder 27)
    In 1831 Long Bridge, connecting Virginia and Washington, D.C., was seriously damaged by high water and ice; it was reconstructed in 1835. Custis offers his suggestions and sketches to the Washington Bridge Company for a temporary rebuilding of the bridge, which involves the use of some hulks of schooners as supports for a narrow crossing. The letter is dated November 13. The original catalog card indicates the letter falls between 1831 and 1835 The letter also has scribbling of Ann Timms at bottom of p.2. Gelman Library purchase this letter in 1982. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - ACED-I special events survey, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    First survey by the Association of Conference and Event Directors International on median salaries of university event directors. Original in: headquarters of the Association at Colorado State University. Donated to Gelman Library by ACED-I in 1994. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Autograph, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    The cartoonist's autograph with a small drawing of the head of a bear saying "Think of me being in this book!" on an album page. Gelman library purchased this item in 1984. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Autograph, 1913 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    The cartoonist's pen and ink autograph at the Washington star with a small drawing of the head of a teddy bear. Berryman is the originator of a cartoon showing President Theodore Roosevelt refusing to shoot a bear cub. Gelman library purchased this item in 1987. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Bedford Brown to John M. McCalla, 03/16/1853 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    Former U.S. Senator Brown says he is enclosing a letter to Senator Augustus C. Dodge, which McCalla may use to obtain the position of Second Auditor of the Treasury Department, in the Pierce Administration. This letter was found in a GW library book in 1938. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Bedford Brown to John M. McCalla, 06/23/1856 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    Former U.S. Senator Brown asks to borrow a pamphlet of speeches defending James Buchanan and asks for McCalla's suppport for Buchanan in the 1856 Presidential election. Found in a GW library book in 1938. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Glenn Brown to U.S. Grant, 3rd, 02/20/1931 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    Glenn Brown was a washington architect and writer. The letter is a thanks Grant for liking his book, 1860-1930, memories. This letter was found in Glenn Brown's 1860-1930, memories. Washington: W.F. Roberts, 1931. (NA9127.W2B85). Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, James Buchanan to Asbury Dickens, 11/01/1847 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    As Secretary of State, Buchanan requests from the Secretary of the Senate a statement for the Biennial Register of the names of the members of the Senate and officers, and the names of printers employed from 1845 Sept. 30 to 1847 Oct. 1. Gelman library purchased this letter in 1986. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Typescripts, 10/7/1973-10/18/1973 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    Columnist. Typescript with annotations of six newspaper columns, each with accompanying teletype proofs, for Oct. 7, 9, 11, 14, 16, 18, 1973. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, 1861 Sept. 8, Traveller's Rest to John G. Pollock, 09/08/1861 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    This Confederate lady named Agnes writes to her cousin in the Confederate Army; mentions a report from a young soldier about the battle of Manassas, and episodes of Union soldiers' mistreatment of local residents and looting of their houses. This is a Civil War personal narrative. Purchased by Gelman library in 1985. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Jefferson Davis to M.C. Meigs, 02/07/1857 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    In this letter Jefferson Davis thanks Meigs for photographs of public buildings in Washington, and thanks him for his service in their construction. The folder also contains a printed portrait of Davis. Gelman Library purchased this letter in 1985. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Gustavus Fellowes Davis to Revd. Dear Sir, 01/23/1823 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    Gustavus Fellowes Davis was a Baptist minister in Connecticut and an auther of religious books. The letter mentions death of Robert B. Semple; says Baptist church work going well; sends some of his publications. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letters, Melvil Dewey to personal frends [sic], 12/10/1931 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    Eightieth birthday letter, using simplified spelling, summing up Dewey's life's accomplishments in establishing the American Library Association, the Lake Placid Club, and working for decimal classification and spelling reform. Accompanied by a letter from Robert Hood, 1932 Jan. 22, telling of Dewey's death on December 26, 1931. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Lydia Sanford Vail Doughty to Princess Cantacuzene, 01/14/1922 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    This letter is a notarized typed letter from Mrs. Doughty, with which she enclosed some souvenirs of General Ulysses S. Grant to the princess, a granddaughter of Grant. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Aldie Mill, undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
    Typescript concerns the history of the Aldie Mill, Aldie, Loudoun County, Va., and its first owner, Charles Fenton Mercer, first president of the C & O Canal Company, Congressman, and worker for the American Colonization Society. Also mentioned is John Singleton Mosby. Author's name is pencilled on first leaf. The original card catalog provides dating between 1950 and 1970. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, John Foster Dulles to Dean William R. Vance, 05/06/1910 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    Typed letter signed to the George Washington University Department of Law, requesting that he be allowed to take moot court work during the 1910-1911 school year. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, James B. Dutton to F. H. Lathin, 10/20/1884 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    The letter mentions Lathin's correspondence with his son, Fred L. Dutton, and sends a box of specimens of white marble from a capstone (of some public building). The letter also mentions that someone from the White House has just come for two small pieces of the same marble. Gelman Library purchased this letter in 1985. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Ralph Emerson to Rev & Dear Brother, 10/02/1832 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    Ralph Emerson was a clergyman and educator, taught ecclesiastical history at Andover Theological Seminary. The letter, possibly to Joseph Emerson, concerns the workshop at Andover Theological Seminary, in which students make boxes for sale; his children; the doctrine of free communion. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Peter Force to Th[omas] Dougherty, 12/02/1818 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    Peter Force was an historian, public printer. In the letter Peter Force writes to the clerk of the House of Representatives detailing the terms of the printing of the 250 copies of: Code of laws for the District of Columbia. Washington: Davis & Force, 1819. Gelman Library purchased this letter in 1986. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Sarah M. Goodrich to Andrew T. Goodrich, 07/09/1811 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    Sarah M. Goodrich writes to her brother about her gratitude that his illness is over and that a soaking rain has finally occurred; mentions the arrival of Mr. and Mrs. Horace Edwards, just from Washington. Mrs. Edwards reports a lack of law and order and Sabbath observance in the capital. Gelman Library purchased this letter in 1985. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Memorandum Vasilii losifovich Gurko to Mikhail Vladimirovich, 02/09/1917 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    A confidential memo to the Chief of the General Staff, General Gurko, to M.V. Rodzianko, Chairman of the Gosudarstvennaia Duma, informing him of the meeting of the 28 members of the Gosudarstvennyi Sovet (Council of the Empire, a consultative body for matters of legislation) and of Gosudarstvennaia Duma (elective legislative assembly). A sober analysis of the situation and needs of the Russian Army and the home front, with suggestions for reorganization of the army, in order to continue the war in the decisive year of 1917. The document is in Russian. This document was found in George Washington University archives. Apparently it was used in a course on Russian history or economics. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Henry Wager Halleck to Major General Samuel P. Heintzelman, 06/26/1863 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    Major General Halleck orders troop movements in the defense of Washington. Gelman Library purchased this letter in 1985. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Joseph Henry to Joseph Cogswell, 07/11/1859 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    Joseph Henry was a scientific researcher on electricity; first secretary and director of the Smithsonian Institution. Letter to Cogswell, superintendent of the Astor Library in New York, requesting the loan of Matthew Young's book, Inquiry into the Principles of Sound, in order to pursue research on sound. Gelman Library purchased this letter in 1984. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Deed, 1833 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    James Hoban, of Washington, D.C. (possibly the son of the architect of the White House), sells his slave, William Gettys, to William Gunton for $325.00. The slave has been held as security for a note with the Bank of Washington. Thomas Munroe, for the Bank, relinquishes ownership of the slave to Gunton. The original card catalog card indicates the deed falls between April 25 and July 01, 1833. Gelman Library purchased this deed in 1984. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Eliza Holbrook to Susan Grout, 07/03/1830 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    This traveler, Eliza Holbrook, describes for her mother the route taken from Danville, Va., using private carriage, stage coach, and steamboat, to Washington, D.C., and the planned trip home to Westborough. She writes enthusiastically of the beauties of Washington. The address page is postmarked July 3, City of Washington. Gelman Library purchased this letter in 1983. Formerly Ind. Ms.
    Eliza Holbrook (1807-1839) was the daughter of Esquire Seth Grout and Susannah Haskell Grout (m. 1794 in Westborough, Worcester County, MA). Source: Vital Records of Westborough, Massachusetts.
  - Letter, Amos D. Hollistan to Sylvanus, 06/15/1852 (Box 5, Folder 52)